# **ASIF IQBAL**

Falls Church, VA · 571-490-2048

asifqwest@gmail.com · LinkedIn: asif2017 · github: asifiqbal

Experienced Senior Linux Systems Engineer with 20 years of experience in installing, configuring, and auditing IT infrastructures in various environments, including public and private data centers, VMware, and the AWS cloud.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### DECEMBER 2021 - PRESENT

#### LINUX SYSTEMS ENGINEER, AMAZON AWS APPCONFIG

Responsible for building and deploying applications across the globe using automation and a  $\rm CI/CD$  pipeline within a fixed deadline.

Significant accomplishments:

- Built and deployed AWS AppConfig service to 6 countries within a tight 8 month deadline using automation and code deployment. I saved the company 3 million dollars per day by streamlining the deployment process to run in parallel using CI/CD.
- Implemented staggered a patching schedule for our **4000**+ hosts to meet our security compliance deadline within 2 weeks with no disruption to service to our customers.

#### **JANUARY 2020 - DECEMBER 2021**

# SENIOR ARCHITECT, ECS FEDERAL / DHS CTOD (CTR)

Responsible for designing and implementing an AWS cloud infrastructure to migrate in-premise environments.

Significant accomplishments:

- Installed, configured, managed, and troubleshot applications in the FedRAMP AWS gov cloud which supports approximately 8,000 users across all components within DHS.
- Improved the Confluence server upgrade process using UNIX file system properties, reducing downtime from 16 hours to 16 seconds. Enabled DHS Confluence to deploy on demand rather than during scheduled downtime.
- Evaluated and assessed an APM solution to ensure it met DHS's FedRAMP security compliance and provided valuable application performance metrics.
- Automated the provisioning and upgrading of 50 EC2 instances using using the suite of Atlassian tools (Bitbucket, Jira, Confluence, Bamboo), **Github**, and **Ansible**.
- Added new <u>features</u> to the opensource PostgreSQL ansible module as a contributor to the **Ansible** postgresql community and meet the needs of our environment.

#### MaRCH 2015 - January 2020

## LEAD ENGINEER, LUMEN (CENTURYLINK)

Responsible for deploying SDWAN globally. Significant accomplishments:

- Installed Linux on 80+ HP DL360 Gen 9 Servers remotely over iLO in multiple countries and provisioned **Versa SDWAN** software on those servers and managed config using **Ansible**.
- Developed a custom ansible SSSD role and automated the distribution of the authentication software on 100+ Linux servers to integrate them with corporate AD for central authentication.
- Configured OpenLDAP based LDAP proxy using **docker-compose** to pass authentication requests to 100+ Linux servers.
- Wrote a script using **Python** for PCI compliance and audit on the IP Backbone.
- Built a tool with **Ruby** for the text-based GUI and **Python** for the backend operation to provision and manage VMs into the VMware environment through vCSA for up to 600 VMs and 100 ESXi servers.
- Built tool with **Jython** to do account management on RSA SecurID servers.
- Installed and configured **Splunk** on 8 X4170 index servers, spread out geographically, using Linux Software RAID and LVM on top, and then provisioned logical volumes to the OS. These servers are used to index events in real-time across the IP backbone environment. Indexed over **18 billion** events, and they are used to investigate and audit issues very quickly.
- Managed central Syslog server for IP Backbone running Syslog-ng 3.5.6 on CentOS 7.
- Managed MTIPS servers by automated patching and auditing and migrating to 2FA authentication

**JUNE 2011 - MARCH 2015** 

SENIOR SYSTEMS ENGINEER, CENTURYLINK

**JuLY 2005 - JUNE 2011** 

LEAD INTERNET SYSTEMS ENGINEER, QWEST COMMUNICATIONS

**MAY 2000 - JUNE 2005** 

INTERNET SYSTEMS ENGINEER I, QWEST COMMUNICATIONS

**EDUCATION** 

MAY 1997

# ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING, THE GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY

Telecommunication Networks, Control Theory, Login Circuit Design, Probability and Statistics, Digital Electronics and Design.

## **S**KILLS

Linux, Ansible, Python, Docker, AWS, Splunk, Bash, MySQL, Aurora PostgreSQL, VMWare, Solaris, RSA SecurID, SSS (AAA), PCI Compliance, TripWire, NMAP, Syslog-NG, TACACS+

## **CERTIFICATES**

Machine Learning Stanford University on Coursera Instructor: Professor Andrew Ng Isssued date: Apr 2018 - No Expiration

Credential ID: LP9KZLGGPKPP

Splunk Certified Power User 6.3 Credential ID: Cert-134556